<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teach Yourself Demoscene in 14 Days</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Teach Yourself Demoscene in 14 Days</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-1---demoscene&#34;&gt;Day 1 - Demoscene?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;image-of-a-demo-2nd-reality&#34;&gt;image of a demo. 2nd reality?&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demoscene&#34;&gt;demoscene&lt;/a&gt; is an underground computer art culture. The term demoscene comes from the word demo, short for demonstration. In the context of the demoscene the word demo means a realtime audiovisual application which is demonstrating the capabilities of the machine it runs on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Demosceners (&amp;ldquo;sceners&amp;rdquo;) are what we call the folks with too much free time that abuse their computer skills to create releases under the demoscene.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-2---find-your-vocation&#34;&gt;Day 2 - Find Your Vocation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the second day of the rest of your life you should figure out what you want to do on the demoscene.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A demo is usually a group effort. Sceners are typically divided into 3 roles:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Graphician - responsible for the artwork, 3d modeling and animations&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Musician - composer and producer of the audio soundtrack&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Coder - programmer of &amp;ldquo;effects&amp;rdquo; and tools that will enable you to get your demo done before the deadline&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can always just do everything yourself, but it obviously requires a high time investment to be proficient in each of the areas. So it&amp;rsquo;s common practice that sceners specialize in one of the roles while &amp;ldquo;outsourcing&amp;rdquo; the others to their group mates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-3---basics-of-graphics&#34;&gt;Day 3 - Basics of Graphics&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The role of doing graphics for a demo is typically supported by a so called graphician. To be a successful graphician in the demoscene you should hopefully enjoy drawing and being randomly creative. There are many tools you can use to draw graphics on the computer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pixel art graphics typically focus on a limited palette of colors and image size. The restrictions come from the oldschool machines that had such limitations on hardware. Small images are typically called sprites. 2D animations are created by cycling between the different frames of a sprite animation. This is the basis of 2d animation. You can &lt;a href=&#34;http://lmgtfy.com/?q=pixel+art+graphics+tools&#34;&gt;google for pixel art graphics tools&lt;/a&gt; and find a whole bunch of modern editors for pixel art. Real sceners will tell you about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pouet.net/prod.php?which=51865&#34;&gt;Grafx2&lt;/a&gt; or the more recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pouet.net/prod.php?which=66976&#34;&gt;Multipaint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-4---basics-of-audio&#34;&gt;Day 4 - Basics of Audio&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are many tools to produce audio freely available for download. Ranging from sample editors to complete DAW (Digital Audio Workstation) solutions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Modern PC demos typically play a pre-recorded final mix of the audio (an mp3 of the track), but the roots of the demoscene involve sample generation and the so called tracker formats. Most demos for oldschool platforms still feature live mixing playback of a tracked track.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-5---basics-of-code&#34;&gt;Day 5 - Basics of Code&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Learning how to program is relatively easy, there are tons of books and free courses on the subject. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.khanacademy.org/&#34;&gt;Khan Academy&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codecademy.com/&#34;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; are as good places as any to learn how to program in general. You&amp;rsquo;ll need to learn about variables, functions, classes, data structures, loops and algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are many programming languages, platforms and styles of programming with their respective zealots preaching &amp;ldquo;the way&amp;rdquo;. Some languages favor certain styles over others but overall you should focus on the language you&amp;rsquo;re most interested in learning or most comfortable with.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-6---tools-and-resources&#34;&gt;Day 6 - Tools and Resources&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to do demos. Some folks enjoy coding everything from scratch, others prefer to use tools to facilitate their work. There are many types of tools, some are commercial (like Maya, 3DS Max, Photoshop), others are open source or freeware. And then we have the so called demotools. Demotools are tools made by demosceners especially to help create better demos. Demotools are especially important if you&amp;rsquo;re working on size limited entries. Some groups develop their internal demotools, others prefer to go open source in order to have more users and raise the bar. The end goal is always to make more good demos.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-7---experiment&#34;&gt;Day 7 - Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;rsquo;re a musician, graphician or coder there is one golden rule in the demoscene: Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to experiment. I promise you on first hand experience that as long as you keep experimenting with things you will eventually release something you are truly proud of. So don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to experiment!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Experiment with tools, experiment with ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Repurpose, remix, discuss things with others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to fail, it&amp;rsquo;s normal to fail, that&amp;rsquo;s how you find interesting things, that&amp;rsquo;s how you learn. So go forth and fail, fail hard, fail misserably, fail often, eventually you will succeed!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-8---achievable-goals&#34;&gt;Day 8 - Achievable Goals&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned there are plenty of ways to make a demo. The only &amp;ldquo;right way&amp;rdquo; is your own way, the one that is the most interesting and fun for you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That being said, an effective rule to ensure a release will be released is to aim for achievable goals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you are not reasonable with your goals you&amp;rsquo;ll soon find yourself demotivated and failing to meet the deadline. For most projects it&amp;rsquo;s better to start small and build on top of what you already have working.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-9---proof-of-concept&#34;&gt;Day 9 - Proof of Concept&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to stop procastinating and get your hands dirty! It&amp;rsquo;s been scientifically proven that anyone spending over 10,000 hours doing any task will eventually become an expert in it. It&amp;rsquo;s very hard for the human mind &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to learn from mistakes. So don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to make them, as previously mentioned: fail often, fail hard, eventually you will succeed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s normal to be afraid of tackling a new challenge. Some people simply lack confidence. Others prefer to brainstorm and try to figure out the best way to attack it before they start. There is nothing wrong with taking your time planning a strategy, but it&amp;rsquo;s all quite useless if you don&amp;rsquo;t actually sit down and try to get it done. So now is the time to try it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-10---deadlines-are-important&#34;&gt;Day 10 - Deadlines Are Important&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nothing like a good old deadline to force you to shape your ideas into a finalized entry.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Demoscene has a natural deadline called the next demoparty. Every demoscener has an &amp;ldquo;oh shit, now i have to make an entry&amp;rdquo; moment. It usually comes right after buying the flight tickets to a demoparty.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sure you could just go to the demoparty and socialize. Nothing wrong with that. Except that everyone at the party will most likely ask if you&amp;rsquo;re working on an entry for the compos, and there is only such a limited amount of plausible excuses you can offer that justify not working on an entry while there is time left.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-11---get-help&#34;&gt;Day 11 - Get Help&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can do great demos alone. Lots of demosceners make demos alone. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you have to.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most demosceners prefer to work in groups. There are advantages and disadvantages to both approaches. Which one you follow entirely depends on your workflow and your ability to find people who share your vision.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Regardless if you work alone or in a demogroup, you may sometimes find yourself in a bit of a pickle halfway through your demo making adventure. If you ever do, you should be aware that you&amp;rsquo;re not alone and that other demosceners tend to be helpful in all sorts of ways:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-12---crunch-time&#34;&gt;Day 12 - Crunch Time&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The good thing about a deadline is that you see it coming months ahead, so technically speaking you can actually plan for something decent and start on time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But ofcourse that the thing about deadlines is that - unless you&amp;rsquo;re a total control freak - they tend to sneak up on you. You start off thinking you have lots of time, so you plan this huge awesome project, and then as time grows shorter you start realizing you aren&amp;rsquo;t actually keeping up with your workplan and that your idea needs to be replaced by something simpler.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-13---the-real-party-is-outside&#34;&gt;Day 13 - The Real Party Is Outside&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Demoparties are where demosceners gather to meet each other, finish their productions and share them on the big screen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At some point some folks realized there was more to life then sitting inside a smelly party place finishing entries. They realized there was a whole world out there to be explored. I&amp;rsquo;m ofcourse talking about the outside of the partyplace, where the demosceners gather to meet each other, talk about how late they are running to finish their productions on time or just idle around, waiting for the compos to start on the big screen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-14---pouet--scene--scene--pouet&#34;&gt;Day 14 - Pouet != Scene &amp;amp;&amp;amp; Scene != Pouet&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After the demoparty comes the official release of your entry.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most entries nowadays are automatically released by the party voting system. This means they will be uploaded to the internet, where dozens of people will be able to download, watch, listen and inevitably leave their public comments on your entry.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You should be aware by now that most people say things online they would never say in person. Keep in mind you cannot see them, you often don&amp;rsquo;t even know them, it&amp;rsquo;s quite hard to understand what they mean exactly, and quite easy to take negative feedback the wrong way. Don&amp;rsquo;t fall for that trap.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
